[Music]
foreign
with any triangle such as the one
pictured here
then place a square on each side of the
triangle so that we have three squares
as pictured
these three squares allow us to create
three new triangles connecting the
adjacent vertices of adjacent squares as
shown here's an interesting question
about the four triangles that we've
created which of them has the greatest
area remember that I'm asking this
question in general not for the specific
triangle that I drew so I want to know
the answer no matter which triangle we
start with is it possible that the
answer doesn't depend on the starting
triangle or will the answer change as
the initial triangle changes
pause the video and see if you can
figure this out on your own
[Music]
it turns out that this is a bit of a
trick question if we erase the three
squares and rotate each of the three
created triangles 90 degrees we get this
shape pictured here in this shape each
of the three created triangles has a
side length that extends one of the side
lengths of the original triangle and
matches that length now when we draw
three altitudes in the original triangle
one perpendicular to each side we see
something interesting not only do the
newly created triangles share a base
with the original triangle they also
share a perpendicular height with the
original triangle this means that the
areas of each of the three created
triangles is equal to the area of the
original triangle but that means that
all four triangles have exactly the same
area
this argument holds No Matter What
triangle we started with it turns out
that whatever triangle you start with
you create three new triangles and when
you rotate them 90 degrees you will
always have one side length that matches
the side length of the original triangle
and you will always get this nicely
glued together three triangle shape so
that when you draw altitudes for the
original triangle those altitudes become
altitudes of one of the three created
triangles